

ALESSANDRO RONCONE

CURRICULUM VITAE

I AM A ROBOTICS ENGINEER AND A DESIGNER



Personal Website: (http://alecive.github.io)

ME AT A GLANCE

- Robotics Engineer with 4 year full-time experience with one of the most advanced robots out there, i.e. the iCub (http://www.icub.org).
- Research interests: **robotics**, multisensory integration, calibration, kinematics, tactile sensing, machine learning, computer vision, sensor fusion.
- Some experience with signal processing, optimization (e.g. IPOPT (https://projects.coin-or.org/lpopt), a software designed for large-scale nonlinear optimization problems), and control engineering.
- *C++ developer*, with a fine knowledge of **YARP** and **iCub** software and libraries.

- Some of my work is available to download at my GitHub page (http://github.com/alecive/), or in Robotology (https://github.com/robotology).
- Long-time Linux user, and active contributor to the Linux FOSS community.
- Graphic Designer and freelancer in the spare time, with a number of successfull projects and employments.
- Obsessed by two things: pixel-perfect graphics, and bit-perfect code.

WHO AM I

Work in progress

SUMMARY

Alessandro Roncone was born in Genova (GE), Italy, 1987. He received his *Bachelor's Degree* in *Biomedical Engineering* with the score of **110/110** with honors at the University of Genova in February 2008. In July 2011 he completed his *Master Degree in NeuroEngineering* (with the score of **110/110** with honors) in the same University. He is currently a *Ph.D. fellow at iCub Facility, Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia, GENOVA, Italy.* The goal of his Ph.D. project is to exploit insights from neuroscience in order to implement a model of **Peripersonal Space (PPS)** on the iCub. The PPS is thought to have a crucial role in humans as well as in animals, acting as an interface between the body and the outside world. It is defined as the space immediately surrounding our bodies, within which objects can be reached and manipulated. It is intimately multisensory, and shows high plasticity: it can be dynamically modulated by incoming information, short term or long term experience, and contextual demands.

EDUCATION

2012 - Present

ISTITUTO ITALIANO DI TECNOLOGIA (IIT), GENOVA IT (HTTP://WWW.IIT.IT)
PH.D. STUDENT IN LIFE AND HUMANOID TECHNOLOGIES

Doctoral course in Robotics, Cognition and Interaction Technologies

2008 - 2011

UNIVERSITÀ DEGLI STUDI DI GENOVA, IT (HTTP://WWW.UNIGE.IT) M.SC. WITH HONORS IN NEUROENGINEERING

Thesis title `Visuo-Haptic Integration for Object Characterization in an Unstructured Environment`

In my thesis, I implemented a system able to leverage on a multisensory-based machine learning system in order to improve the detection and the identification of an object in the robot's workspace. In particular, I implemented an SVM-based system able to integrate between the visual system and the haptic information coming from

the F/T sensor of the iCub robot. The system proved to be successful in improving the vision-based detection of a set of objects by means of the haptic exploration of the same objects.

2005 - 2009

UNIVERSITÀ DEGLI STUDI DI GENOVA, IT (HTTP://WWW.UNIGE.IT) B.SC. WITH HONORS IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING

Thesis title `Support Vector Machine Analysis applied to a Manipulator in a NonStructured Environment`

2005 - 2008

ISICT (ISTITUTO SUPERIORE DI STUDI IN TECNOLOGIE DELL'INFORMAZIONE E DELLA COMUNICAZIONE) (HTTP://WWW.ISICT.IT/) STUDENT (WITH SCOLARSHIP) AT ISICT

ISICT is an acronym, that stands for *Institute of Advanced Studies in Information and Communication Technologies*. It is a consortium created in May 2003 that supports the courses provided by the University of Genoa in order to integrate them with a teaching that is the result of close collaboration between universities, companies and agencies. The goal is to prepare young people for integration into the labor market, and as such I attended a number of additional courses ranging from *Marketing* to *Telecommunications* to *Aerospace Engineering*. I've been also selected for a scolarship, after a thorough examination (only three positions were available).

PUBLICATIONS

2014

IEEE-RAS International Conference On Humanoid Robots

Madrid, Spain, November 18-20, 2014

GAZE STABILIZATION FOR HUMANOID ROBOTS: A COMPREHENSIVE FRAMEWORK

Alessandro Roncone, Ugo Pattacini, Giorgio Metta, and Lorenzo Natale

2014

IEEE-RAS International Conference On Humanoid Robots

Madrid, Spain, November 18-20, 2014

3D STEREO ESTIMATION AND FULLY AUTOMATED LEARNING OF EYE-HAND COORDINATION IN HUMANOID ROBOTS S. R. Fanello, U. Pattacini, I. Gori, V. Tikhanoff, M. Randazzo, A. Roncone, F. Odone, and G. Metta

2014

IEEE International Conference On Robotics And Automation (ICRA)

Hong Kong, China, May 31-June 7, 2014

AUTOMATIC KINEMATIC CHAIN CALIBRATION USING ARTIFICIAL SKIN: SELF-TOUCH IN THE ICUB HUMANOID ROBOT

Alessandro Roncone, Matej Hoffmann, Ugo Pattacini, and Giorgio Metta

It was featured at the IEEE Spectrum Video Friday! (http://spectrum.ieee.org/automaton/robotics/robotics-software/video-friday-robot-racecar-kilobot-display-humanoid-skin)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2012 - Present

Istituto Italiano Di Tecnologia (IIT), Genova IT (Http://Www.lit.lt)

PH.D. FELLOW

Life and Humanoid Technologies

Doctoral course in Robotics, Cognition and Interaction Technologies

Jul. - Oct. 2013

Coop La Lucerna (Http://Cooplalucerna.It/)

ICON DESIGNER

Icon Designer in outsourcing

Coop la Lucerna is a farm right in the middle of Pianura Padana, IT. During the process of restructuring their online offerings, they contacted me in order to implemented a set of icons for their website. The icons were basically a set of 20 vegetables, rendered in a flat and minimal look.

Oct. - Dec. 2011

Magor Corp. (Http://Www.Magorcorp.Com/)

ICON DESIGNER

Icon Designer in outsourcing

I have been contacted in order to design a new set of icons for their tele-collaboration software (it is basically a Skype-like alternative oriented toward telepresence and teleconference). I designed a total of 30 icons.

Feb. - Mar. 2010

The Castle Project (Http://Www.Castleproject.Org.Uk/)

ICON DESIGNER

Icon Designer in outsourcing

I implemented a set of icons for their website. It was a non-profit organization based in Edinburgh aimed toward taking care of drug- and alcohol- addicts, so I had some fun in designing some drug-related icons.

GRAPHIC DESIGN

2013 - Present

FLATWOKEN ICONS

2010 - 2013

AWOKEN ICONS

SKILLS AND TECHNICAL EXPERTISE

Programming Skills:

C++ OPENCV IPOPT MATLAB CSS3 & HTML5 BASH R
PYTHON

CM Skills:

GIT SUBVERSION

Mobile Skills:

ANDROID DEVELOPMENT

OS/Software Skills:

LINUX WINDOWS GIMP INKSCAPE

Languages:

ITALIAN ENGLISH FRENCH

This CV has been auto(-magically) generated from the correspondent page on my personal website. For this reason, there may be some formatting problems here and there. Compilation Date: January 14, 2015